<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: CMS | Max Alcalá Sáinz]]></title>
  <link href="http://maxarturoas.com/blog/categories/cms/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://maxarturoas.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-02T09:33:18-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://maxarturoas.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Max Arturo Alcalá Sáinz]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jumpstarting Into Phile]]></title>
    <link href="http://maxarturoas.com/blog/2014/03/04/jumpstarting-into-phile/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-04T20:02:45-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://maxarturoas.com/blog/2014/03/04/jumpstarting-into-phile</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Back in the day (slowly I feel more attributed to use that phrase), I messed with PHP and MySQL to produce a passable webpage, but alas – with the passage of time, the domain along with the content has been claimed by Oblivion. It seems that everyone is running amock these days with node.js and Django &ndash; where was my own shiny webpage?</p>

<h2>Enter <a href="https://github.com/PhileCMS/Phile">Phile</a>.</h2>

<!-- more -->


<p> It is a flat CMS &ndash; that means there is no database behind it (though I think there is a sqlite DB hidden somewhere, but I shall dive deeper). It uses a clever layout of PHP that enables you to create <code>.md</code> files and have them appear as content in your webpage. That&rsquo;s it &ndash; no messy uploading or indexing. You wouldn&rsquo;t even need a navigation page if you wanted, as the files are linked into your page automagically.</p>

<p>Phile is forked off of Pico CMS, the daddy behind the concept &ndash; but it seems to have enough quirks for people to move into an OO layout of the functions and resources and I must say, it is a pleasure to use.</p>

<p>Take me, for instance &ndash; I am mainly a VBscript guy in my day to day affairs. I am usually time-constrained so I like to be very careful what project I jump into. Knowing that I wanted to kick a site into life, I was about to go with one of the mainstream CMS&rsquo;s (cough, <em>django</em>), yet the flat-file philosophy really captured me. I used to be one of those guys in college that exclusively browsed the web with <a href="http://elinks.or.cz/">eLinks</a> and thoroughly enjoyed XFCE on a 486, so that would fall in line.</p>

<p>Within minutes (and within days of finding a quaint little hosting service that had <em>mod_rewrite</em> activated) I was up and running. It gently exposed me to Twig and rekindled the PHP interest in me, just so I can contribute back. Feel free to check out the GitHub repo, the <a href="http://philecms.github.io/Phile/">summary of features</a> and also James Doyle&rsquo;s shindig. He seems like a smart man.</p>

<p><em>-Max</em></p>

<p><em>&mdash;&mdash;EDITORS NOTE&mdash;&mdash;</em></p>

<p><em>You may see that this webpage is actually hosted in <a href="octopress.org">Octopress</a>, a Jekyll blogging implementation with lots of handy settings in SASS and yml configurations that I recommend you check out. In the effort of looking for the most &lsquo;static&rsquo; CMS system (if you can name Octopress one, it&rsquo;s more of an advanced HTML/CSS/JS rolling engine) I was won over by its advanced configuration settings and an introduction to Ruby at the same time. I still fully recomend Phile and encourage you to help James out if PHP is close to heart.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
