<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: D3 | Max Alcal치 S치inz]]></title>
  <link href="http://maxarturoas.com/blog/categories/d3/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://maxarturoas.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-02T09:33:18-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://maxarturoas.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Max Arturo Alcal치 S치inz]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Top 1000 Stack Overflow Tags, Visualized]]></title>
    <link href="http://maxarturoas.com/blog/2014/07/11/top-1000-stack-overflow-tags-visualized/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-11T15:42:56-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://maxarturoas.com/blog/2014/07/11/top-1000-stack-overflow-tags-visualized</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="http://maxarturoas.com/stylesheets/dataViz/circleDiagram.css"></p>

<script src="http://d3js.org/d3.v3.min.js"></script>


<script type="text/javascript" src="http://maxarturoas.com/javascripts/dataViz/soTagBubbles.js"></script>


<h3>Drag, zoom in and out with your mouse/pinch for relative sizes:</h3>

<div id="tagBubbleChart"></div>


<p><a href="https://data.stackexchange.com/stackoverflow/query/207593/tag-totals-grouped-by-target-tag-synonyms">Source</a></p>

<p>I was very excited when I learned about Stack Exchange&rsquo;s public <a href="https://data.stackexchange.com/">Data Explorer</a> (how come nobody told me about this!!). It is really interesting to see the internal schema (which I assume is that same one used in production), as well as the popular queries to see how far away people are from getting a badge.</p>

<p>I wanted to see how popular different languages and frameworks were around the SO community, so I whipped up a query and set to work&hellip;</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>``` sql Stack Overflow Query
SELECT
  TagTotals.TagName,
  Sum(TagTotals.Count)</p>

<p>FROM(
  SELECT</p>

<pre><code>TagSynonyms.TargetTagName as TagName,
Tags.Count
</code></pre>

<p>  FROM</p>

<pre><code>Tags 
  INNER JOIN 
TagSynonyms ON (
  Tags.TagName = TagSynonyms.SourceTagName
)
</code></pre>

<p>  UNION ALL</p>

<p>  SELECT</p>

<pre><code>Tags.TagName,
Tags.Count
</code></pre>

<p>  FROM</p>

<pre><code>Tags 
  LEFT JOIN 
TagSynonyms ON (
  Tags.TagName = TagSynonyms.SourceTagName
)
</code></pre>

<p>  WHERE</p>

<pre><code>TagSynonyms.SourceTagName IS NULL
</code></pre>

<p>  ) as TagTotals</p>

<p>GROUP BY TagTotals.TagName;</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>That gives you a listing of the number of times a tag has been used in a post. It rolls in tag synonyms, so you get a good idea of the tag groupings. Then I made a JSON out of it and loaded it through d3.layout.pack() to get radii and coordinates for the relative sizes of the bubbles. The text is also scaled through radii for good proportionality:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/tagCircles.jpg" title="&lsquo;Tag Circles&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Hope you like it!</p>

<p><i>EDIT &ndash; Someone on Reddit spotted an oopsie in my SQL&hellip; now it&rsquo;s fixed. Thanks!</i></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[And Now for Some Data...]]></title>
    <link href="http://maxarturoas.com/blog/2014/07/06/and-now-for-some-data-dot-dot-dot/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-06T16:17:04-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://maxarturoas.com/blog/2014/07/06/and-now-for-some-data-dot-dot-dot</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="http://maxarturoas.com/stylesheets/dataViz/barchart.css"></p>

<p>  <script src="http://d3js.org/d3.v3.min.js"></script>
  <script type="text/javascript" src="http://maxarturoas.com/javascripts/dataViz/mexAlcoholReport.js"></script></p>

<p>Finding curated, easy-to-consume data is easier now than ever. Just take a look at <a href="http://quandl.com">quandl</a> and similar projects &ndash; anything you could want is there! This makes things easier for doing inferences and linear regressions on crazy amounts on variables for whatever dataset you&rsquo;d want.</p>

<p>However, I always like looking for some more &lsquo;raw&rsquo;, exotic datasets for me to practice on. Now that I&rsquo;m starting to get a handle on <a href="http://d3js.org/">d3</a>, I&rsquo;ll start throwing in here some of my experiments and see what comes up.</p>

<p>Check this one out:</p>

<h2>Proportion of Alcohol-positive age ranges for roadside Alcohol Test in Hermosillo, Mexico for Dec 2013</h2>

<div id="chartMex"></div>


<p></p>

<!--more-->


<p><a href="http://datos.codeandomexico.org/sl/dataset/prueba-de-alcohol">source</a></p>

<p>This one was generated from the snapshot located in the <a href="http://datos.codeandomexico.org/sl/">Codeando Mexico</a> website. It&rsquo;s a grassroots website for coders to help make government and urban data accessible.</p>

<p>This is a big deal in Mexico, because there are still many local governments and entities that have very little in terms of making their operations and spending data open to the public. Though there has been a lot of progress lately and there is even a <a href="http://inicio.ifai.org.mx/_catalogs/masterpage/ifai.aspx">federal entity</a> devoted to transparency, this website was a welcome surprise.</p>

<p>The dataset is actually pretty rich, including:</p>

<ul>
<li>Age</li>
<li>Sex</li>
<li>Car type</li>
<li>Marital status</li>
<li>Seatbelt on/off</li>
<li>BAC</li>
</ul>


<p>Out of all these, I decided to focus on the age range. The positive status limited me to <strong>N = 199</strong> out of ~2100 entries. Not expecting a lot of surprises, I saw that the age bands actually were quite more centralized than expected, especially if you look at the <a href="http://www.inegi.org.mx/est/contenidos/Proyectos/registros/economicas/accidentes/default.aspx">national INEGI statistics</a> (yeah, you may need a translation for that&hellip;) Though the national statistics are from the victim standpoint for an alcohol-related incident, I was surprised to see that aglomeration in the center.</p>

<p>D3 made it super easy to lay out the elements and sync in the data. If you feel like you want in on how to make your own visualizations, I suggest to read Scott Murray&rsquo;s awesome <a href="http://chimera.labs.oreilly.com/books/1230000000345">Ebook</a> on the subject.</p>

<p>Until next time!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
